<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scotland pulling down the gates of Rome, or, Christ against Antichrist, the Lambs friends against the Dragons followers containing first, Christs herauld proclaiming his second coming, in allarum to most kingdoms of Europe, from the late presaging comet which appeared, December 1680 and January 1681, and now in August 82 ... : secondly, the popish confessions and catechisms, lately dispersed, and their damnable principles examined ...</title>
            <author>Houschone, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4446</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12895696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12895696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 384:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scotland pulling down the gates of Rome, or, Christ against Antichrist, the Lambs friends against the Dragons followers containing first, Christs herauld proclaiming his second coming, in allarum to most kingdoms of Europe, from the late presaging comet which appeared, December 1680 and January 1681, and now in August 82 ... : secondly, the popish confessions and catechisms, lately dispersed, and their damnable principles examined ...</title>
                  <author>Houschone, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Roberts ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication to Arthur, Earl of Anglesey, signed: William Hovschone.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95176:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SCOTLAND Pulling down the Gates of Rome: OR, CHRIST againſt ANTICHRIST.</p>
            <p>THE Lambs Friends againſt the Dragons Followers.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING Firſt, Chriſts Herauld proclaiming his ſecond coming, in Allarum to moſt Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> from the late preſaging Comet which appeared, <hi>December,</hi> 1680. and <hi>January</hi> 1681. and now in <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 82.</p>
            <p>With the Judgment of the Learned in the like preceding caſes; as the Pious and Literate <hi>Beza</hi> upon that Star 1572. and 73. <hi>Widekind</hi> and <hi>Synop. Bohem.</hi> yea, Reverend <hi>Knox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SECONDLY, The Popiſh Confeſſions and Catechiſms, lately diſperſed, and their Damnable Principles examined, promoting a League with <hi>Popery,</hi> to the ruine of <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> teaching impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely to Kill, Murder, and deſtroy, cut the Throats of Thouſands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Roberts,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Fleet-lane.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:95176:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Authors former Labour have found ſuch favourable acceptances, but much more ſingular ſucceſs, by the ſignal preſence of God in the Hearts, of the Serious and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: Theſe are to give Notice, that (the Lord permitting) they may alſo have the Expoſitory in the ſame Method, with Digreſſions, all ſuitable and ſeaſonable for the time, upon the Thirty nine Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95176:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ARTHUR, Lord Baron <hi>Mount Norris, Newport Pannel,</hi> Earl of Angleſey, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Very Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough Truth expoſeth it ſelf (with its naked Breaſt, and thereby make its owners Victors) over Trucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Papiſts!—Yet</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</hi> With Famous <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to caſt your Purple Robe, in your Noble Patrociny over theſe Scriptural Apologies, in order to the more happy preventing of a dreadful Sacrifice, firſt of <hi>Proteſtaniſm,</hi> next of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by a bloody Papiſts and his Aſſociates, a God-daring and Heaven provoking ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, turning the whole fabrick of the Word of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Noſe of Wax, and render the moſt ſerious pretences of a ſpecifick Love-union, to offer their damnable Problems in to the world, whom <hi>David</hi> deſcribes, ſpeak with a heart and a heart. What is mine here, I muſt acknowlegde, my Lord, is not worthy of ſuch Illuſtrious Patronage, but the Truth it ſelf begs your Patrociny, which ever I have heard, and in part do know, doth lodge in your Noble Family, who always have been for Peace, Champions, for Religion, Ornaments, for the Truth, Patriots. Whatever may be the various Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95176:3"/>of mens minds amongſt the very judicious, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Integrals and Circumſtantials of Godlineſs: yet as it is reported of that heroick Spirit of <hi>Boleſlaus,</hi> the moſt materials of his Anceſtors, he cauſed to be kept in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and affixt them as obvious to his eye within his room. Yea, the remarkable paſſages and Vertues of that Famous Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> are combined in your Lordſhips Breaſt. <hi>Nothing I deſire to know, but what Vice and Vertue is, and that I may ſerve the Immortal God aright; ſince ſo much trouble in Life, and pain in Death. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how Rational men, can hound a Phaenomenon to catch a Flie; for my part, I have not only built a Throne to my Son, but a Temple to my God.</hi> Thus he writes to his Son <hi>Commodus</hi> and <hi>Panutius</hi> his Secretary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Noble Lord,</hi> The tranſcendent Properties in your Lordſhips ſerenity of Mind, dexterity of Judgment, doth far ſurpaſs my <hi>Minerva,</hi> which that ancient Philoſopher <hi>Bius</hi> ſpeaketh of a Noble perſon, is here verified, comparing him to a Torch ſhining upon a Mountain. The luſter and radiations of the Sun beam <hi>undervalueth the light of a Candle;</hi> yea, <hi>Aquila non captat muſcus.</hi> Yet thoſe of a lower Orbe, My Lord, through the help of ſuch a Lanthorn may travail on their journey, and paſs through the Thieves of <hi>Jericho.</hi> Thoſe bloody Jeſuits trampling upon Gods Heritage, penning their Panegerick Theams with the blood of Gods Innocents; beating their paradoxical brains, in dipping their quils in the Blood of Monarchs. Now that the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may land your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with top and top gallant, a full aſſurance, and plero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Faith in <hi>Emmanuel's</hi> Land, where the Anchor is laid upon the blood of Jeſus within the vail, ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Ever obliged and Humble Servant in precious Chriſt, WILLIAM HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SCHONE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95176:3"/>
            <head>To the Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal throughout the World, that comely Bride, entirely beloved Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt. From your Head and Husband, King of Kings, Lord of Lords, Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BAbylons</hi> Fire never burnt out; the Dragons flood never cool'd true love to Jeſus; he has been court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and contracting thoſe near ſeventeen hundred years, read the Poſe of his Ring,<note place="margin">Baldazar <hi>to</hi> Beza ſo writes.</note> 
               <hi>I love none but thee alone.</hi> O for Faith, and love to love again. We wear his Contract Ribbons, the ſweet Croſs of Chriſt, freſh and green, you are flouriſhing in all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, return to your Bridegroom fraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the influences of Heaven,<note place="margin">Aurel. <hi>to</hi> Panut.</note> what trouble in life, what pain in death, ſays a Moraliſt, paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Immortality as a tranſparent firmament, yet death to you noble Daughters is ſugared from top to bottom, with moſt pleaſant and ſweet Ingredients; ſo that all Hells Engines can pierce no farther than my skin, ſays one <hi>(Marlorat.)</hi> Here are not <hi>Cains,</hi> Stone-walls, over which death did ſcale, to wrap up the wicked in a Cabinet and Covert of their own ſins. Their Grave ſtinks, Hell, Death, and Judgment, are engraven upon the Tomb; pounds of Judgment, ounces of Wrath, the hot ſcalding of Eternal Vengeance dropping down their Throat, lumps of hell ſhut and thruſt into them, meaſured out from Gods own hand, but O noble Queen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. be not diſmaid, your Husband has wrath in his hands, but love in his heart. Lets ſit in the Chair of Humility and dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of ſelf-denyal; Doves of the valley mourning for their own ſin. Your Marriage in the Clouds ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95176:4"/>be ſolemnized,<note place="margin">Regner Praeden <hi>of</hi> Groningaine.</note> ſaith one, your Corn ſhall not ſhake, your Breard ſhall not wither; <hi>thy due ſhall be as the due of herbs,</hi> Iſai. 34.19. Your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Harbinger proclaims a harveſt, a joyful harveſt though ſorrowful Seed-time. Take a right look of the wheel of Providence, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Zions</hi> whelfare he has on the wheels. A Pagan by the eye of ſenſe could read, <hi>Pharoah Hophras</hi> downfal, why! as Gods peoples Cup was then full of tears, ſo the enemies cup lackt nothing, the wheelings and turnings of time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſoſtris</hi> and another King, drawing the King of <hi>Egypts</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot.</note> was a Looking glaſs to a Pagan, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry motion of a Chariot; one part mounts, to the skie, another preſently in the dirt. The Mountains of iniquity are great, yet Free-grace is greater; though we have broken our ſide of the Contract, yet God has not broken his. The great Commiſſioner of Heaven and earth, is going to hold his Parliament, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> laſt Chapter. To be his Livery-men, ſaith one <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchton;</hi> for ſince the Devil's Badge is a common Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, hang out your flag of defiance; Devil do your worſt? This is the ſecond Summons Chriſt is to hold, a Court of blood-weds againſt Antichriſt; he will plead with all the Lambs of the beaſt, <hi>Ariſe ye dead and come to judgment,</hi> did ſound dreadfully in <hi>Hieronimies</hi> ears before his death, what dreadful Lethargie? what dead ſleep has arreſted the Senſes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kutherfords</hi> Trial of Faith. <hi>Brown</hi> in Life of Faith.</note> ſeized upon the Soul of Men and Women; as if God had Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated the Devil to prevail, either by a providential Commiſſion, to the ſpirit of Errour, or by a Judicial hardning; the ſpring and poiſe of hearts, is broke into nine pieces: No wonder men do not fear to hurt Conſcience; which ſhortly upon themſelves ſhall hold a ſeize, and paſs ſentences. When ye have a eye to the Croſs, look to the Crown; feart Paſſengers known not whether they go, till within half an hour, failing to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuels</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95176:4"/>Land, a hour of his preſence counterballances a thouſand Croſſes, ſaith a Nobleman to the Papiſts, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>Galeaſius de vito;</hi> their Gold periſh with themſelves, who bring Gold in ſuch competition: O narrow necked Heart, that drinks by drops the Wine of Heaven, out of ſuch an Ocean: O for a thouſand hearts to Chriſt: Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold heart, match with the heart burning love of Chriſt; pledge him with the cup of thanks, he has a magnetick vertue, touches as an Adamant, and draws the heart with a blink of his face. No wonder when men as a Gold-ring fell off the ſinger of God; ſo high in count was Man, Angels could not, nor would not lend a hand to help Chriſt ſtopt, and ſet him on the middle finger of God. This is everlaſting love, comely Bride, thanks is all the Rent he ſeeks for, all your enjoyments, and ye ſhall have a Leace of his love! O follow the purſuit of Chriſt, though the Scent be cold, yet he is to be found my Soul, ſaith King <hi>David,</hi> follow after God; fading vanities doth now allure our ſenſes, the prime of our youth is ſacrificed to the Devil! and a heap of Bones ne offer to God: in Youth we are altogether for pleaſure, in Manhood for Credit, in Age for Riches, where will the Heart center? will another world like unto this pleaſe <hi>Alexander,</hi> yet ſhall it be but a empty nothing, hell and earth in one bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall not do, who have taken Mammon to be their God, thoſe who have breathed out their life, ſpent their ſtrength in catching of flies, hownding of vanities. God has ſnatcht them away before they got half a mouthful of their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! will the height of Morality, unparalleld Vertues, center Heroick Spirits: nay,<note place="margin">Marcus Aurel. <hi>to</hi> Caecil <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </note> a Heathen ſhall reſolve the doubt, <hi>Their Vertues ſhall be turned to Vices, who are ignorant of the Gods.</hi> Nay further, and that elegantly, as if the Goſpel were peeping out of a Pagans boſome; thoſe who to build a new Palace, pulls down an old Temple, the whole fabrick
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95176:5"/>of that foundation ſhall ruine the Maſter-builder. Here men work their own ruine with their own hands; when in mens thoughts they have carved and cutted all moſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, looking undoubtedly to anſwer their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Providence fetches them in by the ſhoulder, to oyl the wheel of Providence, and this they ſhall not know. <hi>Hamans</hi> Cruelty, and <hi>Judas</hi> Covetuouſneſs, ſhall anſwer Gods purpoſe, but never their intentions. But herein is peace, making the Believer ſing the Swans Song: the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopy of Gods preſence, that bright cloud that hung over his Diſciples, as a ſcreen ſhall be drawn over them. Yea, Chriſt upon the Mount treating them. Bleſs him for the Scarlet, ſince ye look for the white Robes: what! though Chriſts Church waan, look for a waxing. Your Lord is ſhaking the Tree of life above you, let Antichriſt ſhake his Sword. Fear nothing but deadly ſin, the ſins of the Saints are often ſo deep a die, makes their faces red with ſhame, yet come and welcome with the Lamb of God in our arms. Though the Devils ſparks light upon me, yet ſhall they never burn me. Let me be ground with the teeth of wild beaſts, ſaith one, ſo be it, I be pure bread for God; and after the celebration of the Sacrament, I eat Chriſt yeſterday, he is eating to me, delightful in me. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of Heaven are not under Lock and Key; be open hearted, for Chriſt is open handed. O Daughter, make your Charter rights ſure, get a Paſs for Heaven. The hand writing of Chriſt upon the Soul.<note place="margin">Cyprian Epiſt. 97. Ignatius.</note> To whom ſhall I reſemble your Lord, a Tree in the <hi>Canory Iſland,</hi> Emblem of your Tree of life; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants receive no Rain, but from the branches and leaves of the Tree, as the Roſe-ſol is, the more it drops the more it flows. The ſpirit as the Mother grace, working with the habit, in the renewed faculty, it brings not forth a Baſtard but a full begotten Child of Grace, concuring into every gracious act, though not to the ſubſtance of it, <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95176:5"/>yet to the mode of it; though often the difference is not Patent, as the finger playing upon the harp; the ſpirit bends all the ſtrings of the Soul; the habit is the art tuning the faculty, this is pleaſant. Muſick to Chriſt, not by lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their natural powers, thoſe men wrapt up themſelves in blankets of ignorance,<note place="margin">Thom. P. 9. 9. 3. c.</note> fooliſhly dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſpin righteouſneſs out of their own boſome. O Believers, interpoſe your credit at the Throne, that Chriſt, that bleſſed Bridegroom, may be reconciled to his Bride again. O the prevalency of Prayer with God; the Primitive Chriſtians had the Heavens at their command, in the time of a great drought ſeizing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Emperours Army: he proclaims a Faſt, every man to his God; they prayed ſo hard,<note place="margin">Marcus Aurel.</note> that a ſhowre ran down upon their own Camp, and Hail-ſtones upon their Enemies. Noble Queen, your Saints ſhall ſing when the world ſhall mourn. Our morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and afrernoon is gone, our evening cannot be long: our life is but a day; the Saints ſays come, the Bride ſays come, Miniſter ſays come, the laſt of <hi>Rev.</hi> the world ſays be gone, too good for the wicked, therefore made God, Hell too bad for the righteous, therefore Chriſt took, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizement upon Heaven. O wicked men give your ear one quarter of an hour to the windows of Hell, to hear the Bells of Hell ring, and Trumpets of Heaven ſound: yea, the the Helliſh Spirits would exclaim, bleſſed is the ground the righteous goes on; when Mountains will be clad with Bones, and Rivers run with Blood, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt ſhall be ſpread over the Believer, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95176:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſt againſt Antichriſt:</hi> Or, a Reply to the League-Makers betwixt Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Popery, lately come abroad into the world, attempted of old by <hi>Caſſander, Bartholomeus, Nervus, Seravius, Modeſtus,</hi> renewed by <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons</hi> Rejoynder, and now clad with thread-bare Arguments. <hi>Theophil.</hi> ſaith of <hi>Rome,</hi> Behold here how cheap the Devil buys Souls. No Peace with <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE grant <hi>Maximilian</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> ſet the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned at work, in order to peace; that the one, <hi>viz.</hi> Papiſt, might remit his pride, the other his pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſs; but the Chief Landlord of Souls and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, teaches us to ſet aſunder Worſhips of divers natures, as mingled ſeed, as not only dangerous, but damnable; and however ſome have beaten their brains to hammer out peace, yet could not, yea in Conſcience, but make the breach more wider; ſuch Labyrinths having no end, ſuch ſinks of Errour having no foundation. No pen can reach, nor brain expiate throughout thoſe Cells of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, from which Arminianiſm, Free-willers, Socinians, and what not, have had their birth. Yea, there have been cridled; into which they return as into the vaſt Ocean. However our League-makers are dipping their pens in the gall of bitterneſs, yet ſhall it avail nothing, but verifie that Diſtichion, and accompliſh the pouring out of the laſt Vial, upon all the Limbs of the Beaſt,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Aut mens vulcanum aut forceps indoila fefellit,</l>
               <l>Eir ennen voluit, cudere cudit erin.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95176:6"/>
            <p>Propoſition, A foundation of Religion is over-turned two ways, either flat terms, or by conſequence. Popery and Arminianiſm comes in the laſt way, proclaims, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves all the Articles of Faith, yet denies the meaning of each Article; razing not only the Integral, and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, but the true meaning of the word as the Baſis. As 1. The various ſenſes of the word, ſays our Pamphleteer, doth not unhinge material Articles, nor on them do we build any Fundamental Truth; why then do the Papiſts, as the Scripture, could or would impower them, bend their wit to draw the Popes Temporal Sword out of <hi>Peters</hi> Scabbard, and to fiſh for his Vicaredge with <hi>Peters</hi> nets, taking the help of the Limbeck of the Jeſuites, making the right of Church and State lye under the Popes girdle, unhing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Fundamental Article of Juſtification, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to cloath themſelves with a coat of Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; yea, ſcarce <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Morality, but kill, murder, and deſtroy ſuch truculent practices are mercenary duties, no Truce, no League, no Covenant, keep either to God or Man. In reference to Proteſtants, witneſs their own Patriots, <hi>Vaſquez Alvarez,</hi> but read farther, <hi>Sphanhemins</hi> Contract of <hi>Chamier, Lombard Senten.</hi> If we ſhall view the Monuments of Cruelty, the Heads, Hands, and Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Spirits, wherever they get power, doth call alowd.</p>
            <p>Propoſition, We allow thee will no ſtrength to any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual good, till revived by preventing Grace, the League<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers mitigates thus. The Papiſts and Proteſtants both compare a Man, after the fall to a Priſoner; the Papiſt ſays he's only bound, the Proteſtants ſay, he is not onely bound but dead alſo; both attribute the power of coming out to God; what danger in either Opinion. Anſwer, If the Phyſitian give me a Plaiſter, and leaves me to apply it to my wound, if I will, I impute the cauſe of my deliverance to my ſelf, and yet there is much betwixt a dead man and a ſick man; her errours are wrought like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95176:7"/>Serpents eggs,; for if ſhe taught not Concupiſcence, the inmoſt garment of the Soul; the firſt it puts on, the laſt it puts off, were no ſin, ſhe could not affirm any man could perform the Law; and if ſhe laid not with another hand, the ſandy foundation of Free-will ſhe could not deceive us, they filthy rags of thy unrighteouſneſs. 3. She plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges her ſelf again in the pit ſeeing a cure, not following the ſtar of the Scripture; the Papiſts ſay, Inherent Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the Proteſtant Imputed Righteouſneſs; the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts mean Grace, Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at moſt Evangelical works, or duties, habitual Righteouſnes or good works, actual Righteouſneſs, not ſo formally but our deſervings; the L. M. reconciles thus: both grant its the Blood of Chriſt that delivers what are we concerned whether another pay the debt, as the Proteſtant, or we our ſelves as the Papiſts ſay? But the debt of Juſtice is not payed, till it come out of the hand of Chriſt; the Cautioner the principal muſt not compare; yea, we differ upon the matter, for its nothing but their bits of duties, at the moſt, which they would ſoader with Chriſts Righteouſneſs, which avail nothing out of their own place. I know they make a tergiverſation, and tells us, <hi>Opera tinct a ſanguine Chriſti.</hi> What is this to half the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as <hi>Bradwardane</hi> ſays. Half to man, the other half to God, or flatly deny Imputed Righteouſneſs, as ſome black-mouthed fellows lately do even among Proteſtants, ſcorning at acquaintance with God. 5. We come to the inſtrument applying the wound. The Papiſts grant to Faith a ſhare, but include works in the ſame Category. The League-makers ſpeak very plauſibly, both agree its by the blood of Chriſt we are ſaved; the odds is only in the branches whereby we hold: the Proteſtants lays hold of a ſure one, Faith in Chriſt, the Papiſt of both Faith and Works; now this cuts the ſinews of Faith, altogether looking upon it as a meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous work; or at the beſt, an Evangelical Duty, altogether
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95176:7"/>mercenary, but we have a eye to it, as a condition, or hand touching the Alms, not binding God to our Merits; its nothing but free love, far ſurpaſſing the Fathers love to a Child: Gods Free grace ſo abounding, that the Juſtice of God cannot be known; ſo <hi>Salvian,</hi> a famous Preſbiter in <hi>Meſſalania.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juſtificat fides ſola ſed non ſolitaria.</note> Our Antagoniſt takes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage moſt bitterly to determine moſt ſad concluſions generally upon all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, by reaſon of their promiſcuous conceptions of the applicatory nature of Faith. If there be any offence ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, there is none given; we call it our ſelves, ſay they, Inſtrumental cauſe, which always has one Phyſical influx upon the effect, for to tearm it a paſſive inſtrument, there is no ſuch thing can have being in nature; and if you will grant the name of a condition, formally ſo taken, making Faith and Repentance concomitaneous and coaetaneous, thoſe radical Graces being all ſown at once, though ſome of them peep above the ground before another. All Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Writers agree, <hi>whom God juſtifies, them he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies;</hi> ſo runs the Golden Chain of Election, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. So that Spiritual Sanctification, as the Antinomiah dream, only believer, live looſe if thou wilt, only be in Chriſt, ſin if thou canſt, are the fiery balls of Antichriſt; what if we ſhall grant all demanded, this doth not infer any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efficiency in or with works. If in the leaſt we ſhall put them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and give them that fair <hi>but falſe name, works of Supererrogation, what rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there may be betwixt our works and our Salvation, (what influence they have thereunto be determined, ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and through grace be determined.)</hi> Some grant the ſame relation to illuſtrate it, betwixt the mean and the end; the Scripture points forth, <hi>as ye ſow ye ſhall reap;</hi> becauſe one of theſe Doctors doth in expreſs words ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, (though maintaining Faith directly, and formally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it ſelf in the Church) That the works of a Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95176:8"/>man, upon which the main ſtate of the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie depends, are of themſelves worthy, and God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talliate and pay all ſuch; but poſtpones ſuch a common action of Eternal Life to the Divine promiſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſay they, God is not bound to recompence ſuch, if we look upon his Attributes diſtinct from his Covenant: yea, alſo abſtract from it, <hi>Puteanus Summa Theologiae. Queſt.</hi> 115. <hi>Artic.</hi> 1. <hi>Drob.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>In vain therefore do the Papiſts raiſe duſt, proclaiming to the world notorious lies, which are there refuge, as if it were our Principle, not to approve and encourage the works of the faithful; we grant and approve of a bleſſed harmony, betwixt Faith and Works; yea Works and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life. Yet no caſual relation, but a relation of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſuch reſpect as Mean has to an End. This in a ſober ſenſe, not in a captious; nay, as inſtance, <hi>I have fought a good fight of Faith, henceforth is laid for me a Crown of life;</hi> the fight is needful to obtain the victory, the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in order to obtain the Crown. Nor can we ſay, the conflict of it ſelf produces the Victory, the Crown ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe is freely given.</p>
            <p>What madneſs would it be in any Rational man to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the cauſe of a lights entrance to a chamber, to reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (I ſay) to the demiſſion, letting down, or pulling up of the broads, and yet the world knows, letting down of the broads is, <hi>Conditio ſine qua non.</hi> That the light of Life, the light of Grace, and laſt the life of Glory may enter in; thoſe broads of darkneſs, Atheiſm, Ignorance, Formality, muſt all be pulled up: and this is the ſound Doctrine amongſt all Orthodox Divines. Yea,<note place="margin">Ludovicus le Blanc de Juſtitia.</note> amongſt rational men and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, where the name Proteſtant has not been uſed, <hi>without holineſs we ſhall never ſee Gods face in mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95176:8"/>
            <p>Conceſſions we grant farther, though God doth highly approve of the works of the Regenerate, yet we are not to underſtand them, as if God of themſelves did ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them properly to effectuate Eternal Salvation; yet herein can we, nor ſhall we not, robe thoſe noble actions in the ſight of God, of their juſt value, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per operation, proportionable to their ſphere, being as means natively tending to their end, which is Eternal life and Salvation, conſequently following upon Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and his gracious promiſe. So very ſolidly do the Doctors of the Reformed Churches ſpeak the truth in calm terms, denying denominatively good works to be the proper cauſe, in a ſtrict ſenſe, of our Salvation; why, becauſe they of themſelves do not immediately reach the effect, Gods gracious promiſe mediating betwixt; yet in a more larger, though improper ſenſe, with all our Soul and heart do frame this conceſſion if it would make a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Catholick; honour them with the name of cauſes efficient of our Salvation; but thus, nay as an efficient cauſe, in general is deſcribed, by all the Philoſophers; and ſo morally has a name thus, that in general to be an effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe, whatſoever, in what ever way, has an operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and concourſe into one effect. <hi>Davenant</hi> 39. all we deny, and from that the word of God, a meritorious effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, or properly ſo taken, againſt us is excepted; what can be more clear from the Word of God, that Eternal life is the reward of good works. But Reader know, to ſuch a reward for which we now diſpute, there muſt be thoſe two ingredients abſolutely. 1. That there be a proportion of equality betwixt the labour and the reward, and that by the exact law of Equity it be ſo diſtributed, ſo all our works ſhall be thrown over the bench-bar of Heaven.</p>
            <p>And further, we adde this one conceſſion, if it can avail, though there may not be a proportion of Equality, or poize
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95176:9"/>or valour, yet as one tearms it, a proportion of conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſuch as is betwixt the ſeed and the fruit, the ſower and the reaper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Amongſt things of the ſame order, flowing from the ſame principle, having ſome connexion among themſelves; Grace is glory begun, Heaven upon earth. A famous man explains it further thus, that word (according) holds out all and every relation amongſt two things, betwixt the good works of juſt men and eternal life; good works being a certain moral good, life eternal, a phyſical good, and ſo both agree, though they be not of the ſame kind; and ſo worth and dignity admits of a twofold ſenſe, one conſiſting in a relation of juſtice, as the workman is worthy of his wages; another conſiſting in a certain convenience of nature, <hi>facite fructus peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos dignos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Propoſition, It's not only our, but the worlds wonder, what hath infatuated the great perſons of the earth with this man of this ſin, whoſe life and fortune he ſtill projects, conſidering what ſingular advantages doth accrue to their own intereſt, in trampling upon the man of ſin; how does he clip the feathers of honour, yea dethrones the greateſt of Princes,<note place="margin">Platina, Sabellicus, Krantz, l. 5. cap. 7.</note> the Senate of Cardinals did not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to inveſt themſelves with the power to chooſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Emperours at their pleaſure, as plainly appears by <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand</hi> Electing of <hi>Ralfe,</hi> diſplacing of <hi>Henry,</hi> under which that horrible Idolatry of worſhipping and carrying about of Bread came into the Church, kneeling to the Bread god. <hi>Henry</hi> ſtoutly, as became a Magiſtrate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and ramcountred them with the point of the Sword of Juſtice. Though for a long time he ſubmitted too much, but perceiving how the pulſe of the Senate, like to the Treachery of that Prelate <hi>Thurſtan,</hi> betraying Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, King, and Countrey, to the Popes hands, he muſt needs now declaim himſelf an open enemy to all ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95176:9"/>perſons, for which there is nothing but fire and fagot, grievous Wars againſt him, Excommunicating, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, diſplacing, chooſed a new Emperour, to whom he ſent a Crown of Gold, with this Motto,</p>
            <q>Petra dedit Petrus, Diadema Rodulpho.</q>
            <p>What Tumults, Combuſtions, Devaſtations of Churches and States, have they been actors of? what dreadful villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, under the colour of honeſty, have they learned of the Devil, as one reporteth; how Satan preſcribed ſome rules to the Papiſts for the better defence, when queſtioned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meaning of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Anſelme. Hermolaus. Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Propoſition, Our Pamphleteer leads us now to ſalute this Brother a miſcreant creature, an Arminian Hereſie, to over-turn Gods Eternal Bleſſedneſs, Will, Wiſdom, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and conſequently his whole Eſſence; it ſhall not ſuffice them to write their Panegyrick Theams in beating of their paradoxical brains, dipping their quills in the blood of Gods Innocents, as their old Mother <hi>Babel</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to pull God out of Heaven: we muſt render all the habits of Grace, and the Spirit of God ſuperfluous; Advance the Throne of Free-will, into the Throne of Free grace; cut the Throat of Souls and Life. If God was avenged for the blood of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> much more for the blood of <hi>Abel;</hi> and this is all their colour of honeſty, and picture of lawfulneſs; they are, ſay they, only uſeful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitively, and by no co-efficience, the efficient being help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the habit, in taking away the impediment; yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the vertue of the agent, though not as a natural quality, yet doth the habit influence into the very act which the natural power do chooſe; but beſt of all, with good ground we deny all active concurrence in natural abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to the generating grace in the heart, at the firſt infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of grace into the Soul,<note place="margin">Durand. <hi>and this Pamph.</hi>
               </note> only a paſſive capacity, for in this neither the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95176:10"/>holy Ghoſt, works like a natural Agent, nor man as a moral Agent, in the production of material forms, brought out of the power of the matter, reſulting from the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qualities of the Subject diverſly compounded, and ripened by one external Agent, as thoſe Agents working in the generation of ſecond qualities, ariſing out of the different mixture of the firſt, both which, the qualities, the qualities of the ſubject, concurs with the outward A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, in producing the effect. But this is all the infuſion of the Soul into the body, into whoſe conception and creation it confers nothing; ſo that the whole pack of Moral Vertues, ſo Chriſtionized, cannot kindle a ſpark of this heavenly fire; though they would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that a ſaving intereſt were nothing, but a dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal aſſent of the will: for ſay they, we place Faith in two diſtinct faculties, to flow from two divers principles; but theſe are not diſtinct faculties who have dictinct acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the Underſtanding eſſentially including the Will: And if the Memory be not a diſtinct faculty, becauſe the mind ſufficeth, no more are the Will and Underſtanding. Their object being on the truth and goodneſs of the ſame thing: Chriſt and his Bible being as eſſentially good as true! in order to the practical uſe of thoſe former debates ſpirits, being hot and toiled, travelling throughout floods of errour. Let's ſolace our Souls in the contemplation, yea application of thoſe fundamental Truths, called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by Spirits, who know not whither to reſt; poſting throughout Hell and Earth; and this we ſhall do, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome inferences, and then conſider the Controverſie, abſolutely and reſolutely, before ever a Papiſt had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Inference firſt, what ſad diſtemper attend, yea, poſſeſs, the ſpirits of thoſe men, fluctuating betwixt wind and wave, airt about as the weather cock goes; travail hell over to purchaſe a Proſelite, and make him ſeven times a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95176:10"/>child of the Devil, than one of themſelves. How does Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſute the tentation to their neceſſity; yea, every way qualified to their inclination, what ever may be his ſearch, ſcrutiny, yea knowledge experimental and revealed. Yea, further (revealed) from God, as a Judge to ſome; yet ſtill doth God challenge the firſt room in the Soul, he having that only Prerogative to know the Heart by external Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes. The Devil ſtrangely reads the mind of Man, and knows beſt whether, when, and how to ſow his ſeed: one a ſtranger to the work of Mortification, another grapling after this ſhip wrack of the world, looſes the life in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing the means of life; another of one uneſtabliſhed ſpirit, when natural parts and gifts poſſibly ſwell, yet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty of the grace of God, the Devil ſits down upon the mans lips, orders his pen, frames his tongue, and almoſt weapons againſt the God of Heaven, yea otherwiſe ſink him upon the ſand-bed of preſumption, or chatter him upon the rock of deſpair. <hi>Luther</hi> one day ſpreading his caſe before God, in recapitulating his Treſpaſſes, Satan threw into his Chamber a paper, containing dreadful ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, to which he ſhortly replyed, <hi>I will honour thee for the fire, who came from him, who would adjudge me into eternal torments by dreadful forgeries.</hi> If God ſhall ſugar our cup amongſt many bitter Ingredients, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhall be ſure to drop ſome poyſon.</p>
            <p>Inference, O let principle and practice go hand in hand, the pride of ſome, the peeviſhneſs of others, cannot let ſome recover, when engaged in a ſad practice; I am ſure their maſter did never ſhow ſuch pattern; Chriſtianily doth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſay, <hi>Errare poſſim, haereticus eſſe nolo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inference the third, To tamper in the matters of God, how dangerous is it? but to diſpute the Fundamentals of Godlineſs, how near damnable is it? either of two he muſt ſpeak, the Language of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> or the Language of <hi>Canaan.</hi> There is not a third half way to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhall not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95176:11"/>ſerve our turn, though hundreds huddle themſelves under the notion of Proteſtants, yet by practice declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Proteſtant-Atheiſts, or Proteſtant-Papiſts, putting to their hands to give Gods Ark a wrong touch, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ruines, calls for Temple vengeance. Yea alſo acute wits, intoxicating their brains into crabbed and tickleſome ſubjects, have their ſpirits hell hot, drive on moſt furiouſly, which did ſadly puzzle a profound pate, in too much daubing, which otherwiſe might have produced to the world a notable wit, as <hi>Vorſtius.</hi> But we come cloſely home, have not we ſufficient warrant to take our Fathers Silver Trumpets and ſound to <hi>Europe,</hi> no peace with <hi>Rome,</hi> where to the ſatisfaction of all rational men, without the leaſt breach of Charity, I ſhall illuſtrate and confirm that Poſition in ſerious ſadneſs, a Papiſt <hi>qua</hi> Papiſt, ſo living, ſo dying, cannot be ſaved; and this is ſatisfactory from Reaſon and Religion, if the Lord permit the baſeſt of them, if a zealous Papiſt entering the Chair of God, by a miſcreant Prieſt, to deifie a man, in robbing God of his Prerogative, in pardoning or puniſhing,</p>
            <q>Quod non regina perunca donat.</q>
            <p>We are ſomewhat ſenſible, that multiplicity of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, pungently applying exhortations, cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with a deluded Soul, the one perhaps may have weight with a prophane perſon; we therefore addreſs our ſelves to Gods Tribunal, for the farther confirmation of all who love the truth. In the name of the Son of God, we arreſt Souls under the wrath of an Eternal God, who from ſelf-reſpect, ſelf-honour, or worldly profit, ſhall bring the truth of Chriſt in compoſition (with a penny) of the world, the baſeſt of all his ſlaves; to which perhaps the limbs of the leaſt may probably entice; be it known, the hinge of the Controverſie depends now upon Salvation and Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from which men ſcarcely ſhall retreat when engaged with this Romiſh Fouler, and bloody <hi>Edom.</hi> Cruel as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95176:11"/>
               <hi>Eſau,</hi> his Apparel dyed with the blood of Saints: Alas! too much proof for it, ſo long as men hope to be gainers by Chriſt, ſo long they will follow joyfully, as if the truths of God were not momentous, they turn Religion into a drudge. Chriſt could not be rid of ſenſual Belly-gods, ſo long as he fed them with loaves, <hi>Joh</hi> 6.25. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and preferment will make a man hear diligently, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs openly, preach painfully, till preferments choak both Preachers and Profeſſors; what doth this ſpeak they are all, but ſublunary Soul? villifying a <hi>celeſtial intereſt,</hi> all men ſeek their own, <hi>Vix queritque Jeſus propter Jeſum,</hi> and as the Proverb, do not <hi>diligere Chriſtum in Auguſtino,</hi> its only Chriſt for <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſake, love to the Benefice, Preachers and Profeſſors labour, but the ſpring of life ſays, I love <hi>Auguſtine</hi> becauſe of Chriſts Image, which love ſcruples not upon difficulties in proſperity and adverſity. Though moſt profeſſors now, would have two Summers in one year, Heaven here, and Heaven hereafter; Yet Chriſt who had a right to Heaven, by both Blood and Birth, could not have it without Blood and Blows, its not got with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtroke of Sword, ſaith one ſpeaking of affliction; yet in all this the way of Free-grace is nothing ragged, Chriſt himſelf ſtraws to glory, as with pleaſant flowers, it is but a bed of Roſes to the Believer. Inference the fifth, and that for direction as a general rule, all the Scripture is not delivered in Aphoriſms, or Canons, which occaſion ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of many ignorant Souls, when Satan, with ſome ſhadow of the word of God, drives home a tentation, takes hold of them preſently, as inſtance that of Extream Unction, Pennance, Purgatory, all the Fopperies of <hi>Rome</hi> for our ſafeguard here, take this one argument for all; why would we not ſacrifice our firſt-born with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but no farther, this being ſufficient. Now in one word, to exhauſt all the reaſon of a Souls declining from the way of God, deficiency in holineſs, truth and holineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95176:12"/>inſeparable, and reciprocally, which produces ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sects; the want of this, perſons without the habit of Faith, are Chriſtleſs perſons, duties without the exerciſe of Faith, are duties out of Chriſt; what wonder then Souls can never ſteam Heaven wards, but blind reaſon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded fancy, enthuſiaſtical injection is their Pilot.</p>
            <p>Reader, travail one hour to the Sanctuary, and to the ballance thereof.
<list>
                  <item>1. Thy Principle, whether from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or from Earth.</item>
                  <item>2. Thy Practice.</item>
                  <item>3. Thy Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
                  <item>4. Thy Graces, Faith and Patience of the Saints.</item>
                  <item>5. Thy Converſion in the work of Conviction and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction.</item>
                  <item>6. Thy decay in Grace, <hi>My soul melteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with heavineſs, Pſal.</hi> 119.</item>
                  <item>7. Thy experiences and manifeſtations of Divine Love, time, year, day, month, upon the Sabbath-morning,</item>
               </list>
to record every week all the paſſages of Gods Providence, but much more the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his own perſon, all which God will try, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.9. <hi>Behold I will command, and I will ſift the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>like as corn is ſifted in a ſeive, yet ſhall not a grain fall to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inference, read that of 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. Beloved try the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whether they be of God or no, put Preacher and Preaching to proof, a Crape profeſſion will not do; their Leaders cauſed them to erre, and thoſe that were lead of them are fallen into deſtruction; when Satan glides into Pulpits, and ſow his fair coloured ſeed of Free-will, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal redemption, univerſal grace, objective and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; he ſets the Soul upon the very threſhold of Heaven, but never further; how with ſpecious pretences, promiſing peace, and nothing but war, ſafety and nothing but ſhip-wrackt; Salvation, and nothing but Damnation, which that very Learned man, being the Chariot-driver of this League now intended, could never effectuate; read his own words.</p>
            <div type="extract">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95176:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>George Caſſander</hi> his Legacie, being himſelf orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Emperour to compoſe the Quarrels of the Church.<note place="margin">
                     <bibl>Conſultation, p. <hi>57.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <p>YEt I cannot deny, but in the beginning that many out of a godly zeal and care, were driven into a ſharp and ſevere reproof, of certain manifeſt abuſes, and the principal cauſe of this calamity of the Church, is to be laid upon theſe, who being puft up with a vain inſolent conceit of their Eccleſiaſtical pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, proudly and ſcornfully rejected them, who modeſtly admoniſh them for their Reformation. Wherefore my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, That the Church can never hope for any firm peace, unleſs the beginning, which have been the cauſe of the diſtraction; that is, unleſs thoſe which are in place of Eccleſiaſtical Government, to remit ſomething of theſe too much rigour, and yield ſomewhat to the peace of the Church; but above all, to hearken to the Prayers and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions of godly men, and to correct manifeſt abuſes, according to the rule of Divine Scriptures, yea of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Church, from which our Cardinals, Prelates in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, have ſwerved. This we preſent to your Majeſty, begging without partiality, that ye would ſift the Clergy-men, thoſe Aſſes who ride with Golden Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, when Princes walk on foot; from which we infer, what peace, when they have razed the Fundamentals, can we expect: for ſays another, Biſhops, to the end that they might get Proſelites, the Pagans permitted them to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingle many of their Superſtitions with Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianity,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clowis 1</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King ſent a Crown of Gold to <hi>B. Hormiſda, 513.</hi>
                     </note> content that they ſhould change the name of thoſe falſe Deities, into the bleſſed Martyrs; its ever proper to Errour to retain what has affinity with it ſelf; and foraſmuch as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95176:13"/>that pagan people had extream veneration for their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, the ſame way did it tickle Apoſtatizing Miniſters. Nay, we may take a further reflection, look <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Chapt. 7. for Chriſtians, Tell me where is your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, where is that reverence due by you to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, into whom ye are become exceeding unlike; in your Habit, in your courſe of life, in your Manners, in your Opinions, and finally in your Language. Ye ſtill applaud Antiquity, and yet engroſs Novelty, as much as ye can deviate from the laudable inſtitutions of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, ye retain that which is of no value, ſtopping the Channels of life, and ſtreams of Salvation; ſtopping the Miniſters of Chriſt, in diſcharge of their Meſſage; the Devil has ſitten down upon that mans lips, who would ſhut his Brothers. But let us view that pious and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practice of the Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne, Robert Groaſthead,</hi> containing the Reaſons of his Non conformity to Pope <hi>Innocent;</hi> maintaining, That hindring of Preaching is the ſin next Deviliſm, Paganiſm, Antichriſtianiſm, <hi>Mat. Par. Ann.</hi> 12.53. <hi>p.</hi> 871.</p>
                  <p>Let's yet take a look of the riſe, progreſs, and ſucceſs of thoſe Ceremonies, ſcattered amongſt Reformed Churches, <hi>Ann.</hi> 2007. was very fruitful; for beſides they retained many things that proceeded from the Jews; the Pagans al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo incorporating themſelves into the Chriſtian Church, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingled various Pagan Rites, having infinite number of Superſtitions in their very ordinary converſe. Chriſtians were promiſcouſly converſant with them, not only in the ſame City, but in the ſame Houſe, at the ſame Table, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they reſolve to be acknowledged for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and for the evidence of their Faith, they introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſign of the Croſs; and foraſmuch as it was judged ignominious,<note place="margin">Origen. Hom 3. in Pſal. 39. Cypr. 1. de Haeret. Baptiz.</note> they formed that badge in their Foreheads, going into, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of their Baths, lying down in their beds, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95176:14"/>from their Tables, they thus marked themſelves; yea Satan gains ground even upon account of Martyr dome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honourable, and thoſe who were priſoners for the truth, by a frequent intercourſe of Letters, did maintain a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie with the Church; erroneous perſons to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe more credit to their Errours, and Delinquents to cloak their knavery, ſollicited the Martyrs approbation, they having influence by Letters, interceded with the Church, that they would admit ſuch penitents into their Communion; but ſadly did they abuſe the facile nature of the Martyrs, by over-importunate ſolicitation, or miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now this is only the interceſſion of the Saints, and how much it differs from that which was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward introduced, ye may judge; the man of ſin mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaddle, every one making a Ladder to Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <head>Summary Propoſitions concerning the Star.</head>
            <p>NO ſimply National or Perſonal intereſt can anſwer the great deſign of God; nor does our thoughtfulneſs for to morrow, ſolace our ſpirits, but aggredge our grief, yet man to be as a beaſt, pudling in the ditch of ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, minding only things preſent, clearly ſpeaks out the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationalty and ſenſuality of ſuch a Soul; in vain therefore do ſome confine the end (whether ultimate or mediate) of ſuch a Comet, to the death of a great perſon, as if God concerned himſelf with one Nation, or perſons in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet do we grant a Nation or people once by Contract Engagements, to be the Lords, (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations ſince) may comparatively be ſaid to be more dear and near to God than others, over which he taketh more narrow inſpection,<note place="margin">Wizald. l. 2. Comety Aph. 300.</note> and puniſheth oftner than any Nation; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and other Nations ſince, by Famine,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95176:15"/>Sword, and Peſtilence 2. If God include any ſuch luminary in its circuit and compaſs, to one Iſland or City, and in that interim of time, it doth not ſhew it ſelf to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, it palpably, denotes Gods particular inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into that Iſland for a future ſtroke; for proof where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we have the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> over which Stars perpendicularly appeared, in the forms of fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dragons, with their blue and red ſtreams, to the one end of the Land to the other, to the affrightment of the Inhabitants; ſo that the Moon appeared with Stars ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what remote from her the noon time of the day. 3. Though all the ruines and riſes of Kingdoms and Common-wealths of <hi>Europe,</hi> cannot be deduced from the Poſition, or Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Stars, yet from the conceſſions, concluſions, and exact computation of Chronologers, ſuch Apparitions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver paſt, but in the ſequel, without ſome ſad Judgment; preaching to the world, as the Prophets of old, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the word of the Lord; it ſhall not then be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to reject all the ſad preſages,<note place="margin">Pom. Magdeb. Synopſ. Bohem.</note> which from thence may be probably inferred, and of ſingular conſequence, but much more from ſuch Blazing Comets; though with good ground we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelves in the downfal of the man of ſin, whoſe riſe, reign, rage, ſeven ſeals, ſeven trumpets, ſix vials, hath brought to a end; though we grant ſuch a ſhort tract of time,<note place="margin">Tacitus Annal. Armſaeus Doct. Pot. p. 471.</note> the healing of the wound of the beaſt may be attempted, yet never cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the back of the beaſt being wounded incurable; for the farther confirmation of which time, and poſſible very ſhort, ſhall illuſtrate the Aſſaſſinations, Machinations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of that Antichriſtian party to be nothing but wind, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling to bring forth chaff; and this conſequentially not from any <hi>Impulſive cauſe</hi> in the generation, but ſingularly the glory of his own name. Nor may we think it ſtrange, ſuch Comets 900 years agoe did foretell there rife, now
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95176:15"/>their ruine; the thread of the Propheſie of the Revelation, painting before us the riſe, weig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Babel,</hi> (though and that to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e) all Reformed Churches ſhall ſay, the joy of the delivery is ſo ballance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Croſſes and bitter things, as ſome would rather looſe the joy of the one, than to enjoy for a time, the joy of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. It is granted by moſt Writers, if not by all that ſuch Comets, when ſo illuſtriouſly appearing to the world, never paſs unverified in a ſad Judgment; though God preach ſome years, yet in ſeries he puniſheth: for monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of wrath of God, in the caſe, read <hi>Cameracius, l.</hi> 3. <hi>Julius Obſequies, l. de Prodig.</hi> yet ſo as the Holy Land of God is not limited, either to the kind or the meaſure of the Judgment, as ſome would expound it to portend a plague; as if God had bound up his hands to uſe no other, yea a raging Sword, as well as a ſmiting plague, as the event of this hath evidently been ſeen, which ſome judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly note, ſeldome paſs without all thoſe three, Famine, Sword, and Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>Propoſition, (Whatever hath been, or may be the long ſuffering patience of God, to moſt places of the world to which this was viſible, in <hi>America,</hi> as well as <hi>Aſia,</hi> as appears from the Sermon of that pregnant man of God, Mr. <hi>Increaſe Manner,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Boſton</hi>) yet ſhall we not hood-wink our ſelves, and pull too our caſement when God looks through the firmament, as his window, making the cauſes and appurtenances of this ſignal meſſenger of Chriſt, like to other Meteors; and ſo likewiſe interpret it by low ends; as to portend a Drought, and other frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and childiſh expreſſions, as if we could wheedle God out of his Throne; <hi>be not deceived, for God will not be mocked.</hi> Though without boaſting, by our profeſſion we are bound to ſhew ſo much of Literature, as to vindicate the ſame from all aſperſions; yea, any ſilly Brain may do it, who ever dwelt a Month at <hi>Matheſis.</hi> We ſhall not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95176:16"/>offer all might be afforded, leaſt by ſome we ſhould be miſ-conſtrued Enthuſiaſtick, which we abhor, or in plain ſpeaking of the truth offend; though herein God has remarkably honoured <hi>Britain;</hi> as inſtance, profound <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford,</hi> with the Spirit of Propheſie; yea, of late, godly Mr. <hi>John Walwood;</hi> miſtake us, we ſpeak not of our ſelf, aſſuming any ſuch thing. We ſhall offer therefore to your view, that famous obſervation of a eminent man, <hi>That there has been more blood ſhed Wars ſeen in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, than the whole world beſides; and that moſt of its Kingdoms, if not all, ſhall be involved in blood at once, by its bloody face, and dreadful frowns to all thoſe Kingdoms at once.</hi> And of Reverend <hi>William Perkins, The Goſpel travails every hundred years.</hi> As alſo of that Famous, Faithful, and eminently pious Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> writing to his Son-in-law, and eſpecially found written upon the Margin of <hi>Callopins</hi> Harmony, <hi>Chriſt ſhall be crucified, but glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall his Reſurrection be, Mark</hi> 16.5. And after ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Europe,</hi> O doleful time, happy were the man that could get a Cottage in peace, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 34.7. <hi>The Land ſhall be ſoakt with Blood;</hi> yea, his Son-in-law, directing his Letter to Lady <hi>Lillias Graham,</hi> 1605.17. <hi>Jan. The rich man ſhall not be ſaved by his riches, the wiſe man by his wiſdom, the ſtrong man by his ſtrength; the furbiſhing Sword being drawn, glittereth, it ſhall not return till it be drunk with the blood of men, Jer.</hi> 46.9. <hi>The Sword ſhall be made drunk with blood.</hi> We add onely that of <hi>Beza,</hi> yet upon record this is the Star, <hi>which to the City ſmall of</hi> David <hi>King; the three wiſe men from out the eaſt did bring, returning now, declares that Chriſt returns in might, what hap to each it doth portend, the God of Gods doth know.</hi> The ſequel of which was marked, with inteſtine and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Sword; though this hath a main eye to the ſecond coming of Chriſt, Scriptures near fulfilled, mockers of the Goſpel ſtigmatized. Yea in the Primitive times, the earth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95176:16"/>ſwallowed them up quick, as the Hierapolians for mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God: though herein none can be punctual and poſitive in ſobriety, without reflection upon our Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Judicious, and Pious Fathers, <hi>Melancton, Regner Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Shelto</hi> making the world to ſtand ſix thouſand years, the laſt two thouſand were to be ſhortned for the Elects ſake. Certain it is, things haſten to a cloſe, Grace and Literature, not ſo as when God raiſed up <hi>Valla,</hi> and <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> a decay in Godlineſs, prodigal, liberal, rich men deemed beſt men; covetous good Husbands, truth perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, error in credit, the world upſide down, the whole fabrick out of order, great heats, great colds, great drought, great rains, the fruitfulneſs of the field decayed, the world tottering upon its foundation; the earth groans to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of ſuch a heavy load, a burden of ſin; the very beaſt ſhews its reſentment of a ſinful generation, the sky is defiled, all is polluted, love to God, and mutually to one another is gone. <hi>Cornelius</hi> a <hi>Lapide</hi> brings in the very beaſt, as coveting to be engrafted or united to this or that godly man. O to do him ſervice, for now I fight againſt God, turn and lament ye wicked men, the gates of hell are of braſs, their bars of iron, they will never break; lazy daughters, awake to zeal, for as the bels which hung in <hi>Aarons</hi> garment, could not want Pomegranats, ſo God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not ſound without fruit. The wrath of God is but kindling to make our bed in ſorrow, how are we at league with the Devil, and at war with God; no peace with God, and no peace with man; its true, it was ſaid of <hi>Spain,</hi> at peace with all the world, but at war with their God; how in the reaſon can men look to live with God, and yet cannot live a day with his Saints! O that God would put a Lump of Hell, and a Lump of Heaven in them! the ſhadow of ſin in Heaven would afright the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95176:17"/>
            <p>Reader, I charge thee in the name of the Eternal God, extenuate not thy ſin! however ſome eſcape ſmaller ſtrokes, yet in order to a farther Judgment, looking back over our ſhoulder, not bowing the knee in the eye of ſenſe! ſo conſulting argues a peeviſh humour to a roving Soul; and yet all Mankind ſhall forfeit their right of glory for the firſt, and <hi>Lots</hi> wife remains a rocky Mineral of Eternal vengeance for the ſecond; and <hi>Daniel</hi> a Crown of life, ſhall have for the third; the reviving preſence of God is loſt either ways, what do we ſpeak a Romance; yet truth to others when black-mouthed <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>Sh.</hi> can be waged by Hell,<note place="margin">O Sin thy death, O ſin Ile be for killing the moſt hight, Corruption, thy life Ile take, for thou haſt wounded me.</note> to raile againſt Gods Anointed, and declaim all perſonal acquaintance with God, as folly and fancie; with ſuch Delinquents we ſhall debate the matter before Gods Tribunal; the Bible is not their rule, the Spirit of God their Councellour. <hi>Luther</hi> can tell us, he can dwell in hell, and Chriſt were there; his gracious preſence counterballances all afflictions. Rationiſts can tell us, the marrow of Philoſophy conſiſted in ſolacing of the Mind; much more the ſubſtance of Divinity. The Pagan <hi>Indian</hi> replyed well to the Spaniſh Prieſt, when threatning him to Popery, with fire and fagot, <hi>What ſhall I have if I do ſo, whether ſhall we go after?</hi> they anſwer to Heaven, Life, and Salvation, <hi>I would rather,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>live in Hell, as dwell in Heaven with ſuch company.</hi> The bells of Hell ring the Trumpets of Heaven ſound, half a hour in Hell, and a hour in Heaven; the terrour of the one, the joy of the other, a Proclamation at the gates of Hell, come out and repent, ſhould reſolve our doubts; though ſome go to the Devil with a light candle in their hand; yea creeping under a buſh of profeſſion as they go; who can abide Eternal Torments, tearing and rending of the caul of the heart; like to a fierce bird, tearing, dab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, rending of a Liver, yet no end of the ſame, ſo <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vater</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95176:17"/>compares it. Reader, do the favour to thy own Souls intereſt, unite thy thoughts, compoſe thy affections, retire one hour, and to thee O Chriſtian I appeal; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of the preſence of God, the ebbing and flowing of the Spirit of God. Naturaliſts, who never knew Chriſt, can prove this Sea-ſtork, and purſuing ordinarily another fiſh, whoſe ſins are as wings to mount above the water, to preſerve its life, doth take ſo much water, as to make it flee more nimble, and when once dried again, preſently falls down. When once a Chriſtian is faſtned with the Spirit of God, it ſoars aloft, as the ſeed of the earth is brought into fruitfulneſs by continual ſhowers, the ſeed of grace in the heart is renewed by the acts of the Spirit ſhed upon us; 1. by Molification; 2. Refrigeration; 3. Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition, I will ſprinkle thee with water.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
